ILGWU. Local 117 minutes, 5780/034
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
ILGWU. Local 117 minutes
1934-1973.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 117.
5780/034
2.5 cubic feet
2.5 linear feet
Minutes, reports.
Records of International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 117, Cloak, Suit, Infants' and Childrens' Coat Operators and Sample Makers' Union. Includes Executive Board and Membership minutes as well as Managers' reports.
5491300
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff
Date completed:
1999
EAD encoding:
Casey Westerman, 2003Cheryl Beredo, May 2011
Biographical / Historical
The International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union was founded in New York City in 1900 by mostly Socialist immigrant workers who sought to unite the various crafts in the growing women's garment industry. The union soon reflected changes in the sector and rapidly organized thousands of unskilled and semi-skilled women, mostly Jewish and Italian young immigrants. Exemplifying the "new unionism," the ILGWU led two of the most widespread and best-known industrial strikes of the early Twentieth Century: the shirtwaist makers' strike of 1909 in New York City and the cloak makers' strike of 1910 in Chicago. The union also tried to adapt to the fragmented and unstable nature of the industry. It adopted the "protocol of peace," a system of industrial relations that attempted to ensure stability and limit strikes and production disruption by providing for an arbitration system to resolve disputes.
The ILGWU exemplified the European-style social unionism of its founding members. They pursued bread and butter issues but provided educational opportunities, benefits, and social programs to union members as well. In 1919, the ILGWU became the first American union to negotiate an unemployment compensation fund that was contributed to by its employers. The ILGWU also pioneered in the establishment of an extremely progressive health care program for its members which included not only regional Union Health Centers but also a resort for union workers, known as Unity House. The Union also had an imaginative and pioneering Education Department which not only trained workers in traditional union techniques, but provided courses in citizenship and the English language.
David Dubinsky, an immigrant from Belarus who came to the US in 1911, provided strong leadership that led to unprecedented growth in the union during his presidency from 1932 to 1966. He led the union through successful internal anti-communist struggles, built on the ascendancy of industrial unionism by encouraging the formation of the Committee for Industrial Organization, and helped the union become an important political force in New York City and state politics, and in the national Democratic Party and Liberal Party as well.
In the period following the Second World War, the union suffered a decline in membership as manufacturers avoided unionization and took advantage of less expensive labor by moving shops from the urban centers in the northeast to the south, and later abroad. The ethnic and racial character of the ILGWU also changed as European immigrants were supplanted by Asians, Latin Americans, African- Americans, and immigrants from the Caribbean.
In July 1995 the ILGWU merged with the Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union (ACTWU) at a joint convention, forming UNITE (Union of Needletrades, Industrial and Textile Employees). At the time the new union had a membership of about 250,000 in the United States, Canada, and Puerto Rico.
Biographical / Historical
Chartered in 1931, Local 117 of the International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union (ILGWU), also known as the Cloak, Suit, Infants' and Childrens' Coat Operators and Sample Makers' Union, was created with the merger of Local 1 and Local 17 and based in New York, New York.
Scope and Contents
Records of International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union Local 117, Cloak, Suit, Infants' and Childrens' Coat Operators and Sample Makers' Union. Includes Executive Board and Membership minutes as well as Managers' reports.
Conditions Governing Access
The ILGWU Records, except for publications and materials produced for publication, are restricted. Materials created prior to twenty years from the current date are open to researchers only with prior written permission from the Director of the Kheel Center; materials created during the past twenty-years are closed; the minutes of the General Executive Board are closed. For more information contact the Kheel Center.
Related Materials
5780. ILGWU records
General
"Permanent deposit"
Women's clothing industry--United States.; Labor unions--Clothing workers--United States.; Clothing workers--United States.; Industrial relations--United States.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union.; International Ladies' Garment Workers' Union. Local 117.
5491300
- Minutes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Jan.-June, 1936. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  July-Dec., 1936. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Jan.-June, 1937. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  July-Dec., 1937. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Jan.-June, 1938. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  July-Dec., 1938. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Jan.-June, 1939. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1939 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  July-Dec., 1939. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Jan.-June, 1940. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  July-Dec., 1940. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1941 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Yiddish
- Minutes, 1942 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Minutes, 1943 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Minutes, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Jan.-Dec., 1944. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Minutes, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Minutes, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- Minutes, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Minutes, 1949 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- Minutes, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Nov. 1960 - Dec. 1961. Yiddish. Incl. Correspondence in English
- Minutes, 1962-1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Jan. 1962 - Dec. 1963. Yiddish
- Minutes, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Jan.-Dec., 1964. Yiddish
- Minutes and Managers Reports from United Cloak, Suit, Infants and Children's Coat Operators and Sample Makers Union, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  Jan.-Dec., 1965. Minutes in Yiddish. Reports in English
- Minutes of Executive Board, 1966-1967 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  English
- Minutes of Executive Board, 1968-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  Jan. 1968 - Dec. 1969. English
- Minutes, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  Jan. 1970 - Oct. 1971. English
- Minutes, 1971-1973 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  Nov. 1971 - Nov. 1973. English